A Guide to the Lobdell Car Wheel Company Account Books, 1881-1902
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech
Lobdell Car Wheel Company Account Books, 1881-1902
Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1940-019
Some of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
2.9 Cubic Feet; 9 boxes
This collection contains the records of a Smyth and Wythe County, Virginia furnace and store operations of the Lobdell Car Wheel Company, including customer store accounts, payroll records, and furnace operation reports.
Lobdell Car Wheel Company
Administrative Information
Conditions Governing Access
The collection is open for research.
Source of Acquisition
The Lobdell Car Wheel Company Account Books were donated to the university in 1939 or 1940 and transferred to Special Collections and University Archives in 1955.
Existence and Location of Copies
Some of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
Administrative History
The Lobdell Car Wheel Company had its beginnings in 1830, when Jonathon Bonney and Charles Bush established a small foundry in Wilmington, Delaware. By 1867, the year it was incorporated as the Lobdell Car Wheel Company, the business had added partner George Lobdell and become the world's largest manufacturer of wheels for railroad cars.
White Rock Furnace, located five miles from Rural Retreat and near the head of Cripple Creek in Smyth County, was among the Lobdell Car Wheel Company's operations in Virginia. Built in 1875, and originally known as the Panic Furnace, the White Rock was purchased in 1880 by Lobdell, which also bought Brown Hill Furnace in neighboring Wythe County. The White Rock ceased operation in the early 20th century, when the company found it more cost effective to purchase, rather than mine and manufacture, its iron.
Scope and Content
This collection contains account books relating to the southwestern Virginia business concerns of the Lobdell Car Wheel Company. Most of the records seem to have originated with the White Rock Furnace in Smyth County. Included are customer account records from the company's store, payroll ledgers, invoices, correspondence, and furnace operation records and reports. Much of the correspondence is addressed directly to Jacob W. Lantz, who managed Lobdell's farm and conducted other business for the company.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by ledger type, then chronologically.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Archival Material
See the Jacob W. Lantz Papers, Ms1975-003, also in Special Collections and University Archives.
Rights Statement for Archival Description
The guide to the Lobdell Car Wheel Company Account Books by Special Collections and University Archives, Virginia Tech, is licensed under a CC0 (https://creativecommons.org/share-your- work/public-domain/cc0/).
Index Terms
Subjects:
Account books; Iron foundries -- Virginia; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Smyth County (Va.); Wythe County (Va.)
Contents List
Some of this collection has been digitized and is available online.
- Store customer accounts, 1881-1883 (Box 1, Item 1-2)
- Store customer accounts, 1885-1889 (Box 2, Item 1)
- Store customer accounts, 1889-1891 (Box 3, Item 1-2)
- Store customer accounts, 1891-1894 (Box 4, Item 1)
- White Rock Furnace monthly account balances, 1884-1887 (Box 4, Item 2)
  Scope and Content
  This volume also contains store customer accounts, 1888-1889.
- Freight accounts, 1888-1893 (Box 4, Item 3)
- Store day book, 1882-1883 (Box 5, Item 1)
- Store day book, May-Oct 1900 (Box 5, Item 2-3)
- Incoming correspondence, 1890-1895, [bound volume] (Box 6, Item 1)
- Invoices and receipts, 1887-1890, [bound volume] (Box 7, Item 1)
- Invoices and receipts, 1890-1893, [bound volume] (Box 8, Item 1)
- Brown Hill Store inventories and reports, 1881-1883 (Box 9, Item 1)
- Labor expenses, 1897-1901 (Box 9, Item 2)
- Farm and stables payroll records, 1892-1895 (Box 9, Item 3)
- White Rock Furnace daily operation reports, 1881-1902 (Box 9, Item 4)
- White Rock furnace payroll records, 1881-1890 (Box 9, Item 5)